Okay, last section of this chapter, gestational pathology.
The first disorder that we want to talk about is ectopic pregnancy.
So the idea here is that we get implantation of a fertilized ovum at a site other than the uterine wall.
The most common site is the lumen of the fallopian tube, and the key risk factor is scarring.
So let's remind ourselves, when might we see scarring in the lumen of the fallopian tube?
Well, one example would be pelvic inflammatory disease, where the patients get inflammation of the upper portion of the female genital tract,
and so that could result in scarring, which would increase the risk of ectopic pregnancy.
And another example would be endometriosis.
Remember that if endometriosis involves a tube, then there can be damage to the tube with scarring,
which could then result in an ectopic pregnancy as well, in particular, an ectopic tubal pregnancy.
Here's what an ectopic pregnancy would look like.
This is the fallopian tube.
Clearly, this region of the fallopian tube is expanded,
and you can see this area of hemorrhage at this point where the tube is actually ruptured.
The classic presentation is that the patient comes in with lower quadrant abdominal pain.
Now, when a patient comes in with lower quadrant abdominal pain, there's a lot of things that you can think about.
But one of the sort of general principles is anytime you have someone with lower quadrant abdominal pain
and you're worried about anything severe, you always want to think about doing a pregnancy test,
especially in a woman that's within that range of age in which she could be pregnant.
So pregnancy test is a very important initial test in a patient that's got abdominal pain,
presenting, for example, as an acute abdomen.
So that's a classic presentation, and it's potentially a surgical emergency
because obviously the tube can rupture.
Another possible disorder of gestation is called a spontaneous abortion.
This is where there's a miscarriage of the fetus, usually 20 weeks before gestation,
so at 20 weeks or before, and so that would be a spontaneous abortion.
Now, what we should recognize is that this is relatively common, so that's one point.
And another point is that it is recognizable in up to one-fourth of pregnancies,
so that's how common it actually is.
How will the patients present?
They have vaginal bleeding with cramp-like pain, and they pass fetal tissue.
So that's the classic presentation of a spontaneous abortion.
What's important to remember is that this is relatively common, but it's due to chromosomal anomalies.
And, you know, it's not due to exercise or stress, etc.
It's most often thought to be due to chromosomal anomalies.
There are some other important causes to be aware of, but the classic cause is chromosomal anomalies.
One important cause to be aware of would be hypercoagulable state.
Can you remind me which patient that we've already talked about in a prior chapter could develop recurrent pregnancy loss
as part of the complication of their hypercoagulable state?
Remember, patients with lupus who have lupus anticoagulant get a hypercoagulable state,
and one of the ways by which that can manifest itself is with recurrent pregnancy loss.
Congenital infection can result in a spontaneous abortion,
and exposure to teratogens can result in a spontaneous abortion.
Now, when you think about teratogens, it's a little more, it's a little complex.
It depends on when they're actually exposed.
So, for example, when you have exposure to a teratogen, if it's within the first two weeks
and the dose is significant and it's a significant teratogen, that can result in spontaneous abortion.
Classically, if it occurs between weeks three to weeks eight, then you think about a risk of organ malformation.
And if it occurs after that, any time from months three to months nine,
then you think about a risk of organ hypoplasia.
And so these are some of the things that can occur with teratogens.
Now, in your book, I've put in a list of teratogens, a table, with some very classic high-yield changes that can occur,
and so I'll ask you to review that there.
I really don't need to read to you.
Most of the explanation is just in the principles, and I'm giving you that.
Placenta previa is an implantation of the placenta in the lower uterine segment.
And it's very simple.
Here's basically the way you would think about it.
This is the cervix, and then this is the uterine wall.
And normally, the placenta would implant somewhere up here.
If the placenta implants here in the lower uterine segment, what's going to happen is that you're going to get a preview of the placenta, right?
Either you're going to be able to see it, or you're going to be able to feel it.
So it's as if you get a preview of the placenta, and that's placenta previa.
It's when the placenta overlies the cervical os.
This presents as third trimester bleeding, and it often requires delivery of the fetus by C-section.
And that's because, imagine if there's baby, and baby's trying to get through here, as baby tries to get through here, that's going to compress the placenta.
And if you compress the placenta, you're basically compressing the blood source of the baby.
And so that could result in fetal distress.
And so placenta previa, if it really exists and it continues throughout the very late portion of the pregnancy, it would be treated with a, or it would require a C-section.
Another complication is called placental abruption, and what's placental abruption?
That would be where you have a placenta, like this, and the placenta abruptly begins to separate from the uterine wall.
So that's placenta abruption, and that's what I've stated here.
Separation of the placenta from the decidua prior to delivery.
This is a common cause of stillbirth, and it presents with third trimester bleeding and fetal insufficiency.
And that kind of makes sense, because if you go back here, and you've got this uterus, and you've got this placenta up here, if you begin to separate the placenta from the wall, well, then you've cut off the source of, you know, the baby's source of blood, or the baby's source of oxygen, I should say.
And so what's going to happen then is that that's going to result in fetal distress.
So there'll be fetal insufficiency and a risk of stillbirth.
And at the same time, as this placenta begins to separate, you're going to get bleeding between the placenta and the area of separation.
And so that's going to result in third trimester bleeding.
Classically, when you remove the placenta in these patients with placental abruption, you see that there is blood on the surface of the placenta that was up against the decidua, the maternal surface.
That's called the maternal surface, and there'll be a very bloody maternal surface with clots along its surface.
Placenta accreta is when you have improper implantation of the placenta directly into the myometrium.
Now, let's review this and remind ourselves that if this is the uterine wall, then what you've got here is decidua, which is really endometrium that has been put under the effect of progesterone.
And then after that, you've got myometrium, right?
And so normally, when the placenta comes in, the placenta will come in here, and it will attach to the decidua.
That's the normal implantation of the placenta.
However, if there is no decidua or there's minimal decidua, the placenta will attach to the myometrium, and when it attaches to the myometrium, that's called placenta accreta.
It becomes stuck.
Now, how is this going to present?
This is going to present with difficulty in delivering the placenta.
Remember that after the baby is delivered, the next thing we do is we deliver the placenta.
However, the placenta is stuck, so we won't be able to deliver it very well.
So that's the difficult delivery of the placenta.
And they get postpartum bleeding, because as that placenta is sort of partially off and partially on, there's going to be tremendous bleeding.
And this often results in hysterectomy, because the placenta can't be taken off,
and so the entire uterus has to be removed because of the massive amounts of blood loss that are occurring during that delivery.
Pre-eclampsia is pregnancy-induced hypertension and proteinuria, and the patients also have edema because they lose protein in their urine.
This classically arises in the third trimester, and it's a problem of the maternal-fetal-vascular interface.
Basically, when you have pre-eclampsia, it's due to the placenta.
Something is happening with the placenta that results in this complication.
Now, a few important points.
First of all, this is seen in about 5% of pregnancies.
The patients can have hypertension, and the hypertension can be really severe.
It can be almost to the level of malignant hypertension, where the patients actually get headaches and visual abnormalities, et cetera.
Now, one thing to bear in mind is that when you have a patient with pre-eclampsia, you're going to have very high blood pressure,
and that very high blood pressure is going to result in a classic finding, which is called fibrinoid necrosis.
And that fibrinoid necrosis could be seen in the vessels of the placenta.
So this is a very important association.
That is that patients with pre-eclampsia may have fibrinoid necrosis in the vessels of the placenta.
Of course, this is due to an abnormality of the placenta at the fetal-maternal interface,
and so if you remove the placenta, this will actually resolve.
That's pre-eclampsia.
Now, if a patient has pre-eclampsia, and then they subsequently on top of that develop seizures,
that's called eclampsia, and that mandates delivery of the placenta.
So when a patient's got eclampsia, then the baby has to be delivered, the placenta has to be removed because of that complication, too.
And, of course, that would resolve the eclampsia.
Another complication of pre-eclampsia or a progression of pre-eclampsia would be called HELP.
H stands for hemolysis, EL stands for elevated liver enzymes, and LP stands for low platelets.
This is an example of a thrombotic microangiopathy in which the patients get thrombi, in particular platelet thrombi,
within the small blood vessels of the liver.
So the idea is the following, and you're familiar with this now by the time we've gotten to this discussion,
and that is that you've got the liver here.
Now, this is a blood vessel going through the liver, and we get a little bit of a platelet thrombus here,
and that platelet thrombus is in a small vessel.
When the red blood cell tries to go across it, it gets sheared, and a schistocyte is going to be produced.
So these patients are going to have hemolysis because they're shearing their red blood cells.
They're going to have elevated liver enzymes because this is going to result in infarction of some of the liver tissue,
because there's going to be a lack of good blood flow going through the liver,
and they're going to have low platelets because these platelets are being used up to form these little thrombi,
these platelet thrombi.
And so that's the classic findings of HELP.
Now, what do we say here in your text?
We say that it's preeclampsia with thrombotic microangiopathy involving the liver.
There's hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme, and low platelets, which basically the name tells you.
Next disorder is called sudden infant death syndrome.
This is where a child dies suddenly.
It's a healthy infant, dies for some unknown cause, or really without any direct cause.
Classically, it must occur between one month to one year of age.
So if a child is greater than a year, we don't call that sudden infant death syndrome.
If they're less than a month, we don't call that sudden infant death syndrome.
Patients usually die while they're sleeping, and the risk factors include sleeping on the stomach.
Now, also, smoking in the household increases the risk, and that is something that examiners like to go after,
because, again, we always want to be able to alert our patients to the risks of smoking.
So this is something to be aware of, sudden infant death syndrome.
The next and last discussion in this section deals with hydatidiform mull.
What is hydatidiform mull?
Well, basically, the idea here is that you have a conception, but it's an abnormal conception,
and instead of growing a baby, you grow abnormal placental tissue.
That's the underlying idea.
You get these villi.
Remember that the villi are the functional unit of the placenta.
So you get these villi, and the villi are very edematous,
and those edematous villi have excessive proliferation of the cells around them,
and remember that the cells that surround the villi are the trophoblast, and that's called the hydatidiform mull.
So it's an abnormal conception characterized by swollen and edematous villi
with proliferation of trophoblasts around those villi.
Now, when a woman gets a hydatidiform mull, she doesn't know that she's got that mull growing within her.
Her uterus is going to expand, and she's going to think that she's got a normal pregnancy.
A couple unique things that will be seen in this patient is that the uterus will be bigger than normal.
So, for example, her uterus would be larger than what you would expect to be for her dates of gestation.
And number two, her beta-HCG will be higher than you would expect for those dates of gestation.
You can look at the beta-HCG along the chart or timeline of gestation,
and as you progress through the gestation, the beta-HCG goes up, especially in the first trimester.
And so in this particular case, she's going to seem like she's got a normal pregnancy.
The uterus will get bigger and the beta-HCG will be up.
However, the uterus will be bigger than normal, and the beta-HCG would be higher than normal.
Now, eventually what will happen, or classically what would happen if there was no prenatal care,
that the woman would begin to pass these little grape-like masses.
See how these kind of look like grapes?
So these are the grape-like masses that a woman with a molar pregnancy would actually pass through the vaginal canal.
And that's the classic presentation.
Usually it occurs in the early second trimester, and that would be seen if there's no prenatal care.
Now, what are those grape-like masses?
Remember that the normal structure of the placenta, the functional unit, is called the villus.
So this would be the villus, and the villus is surrounded by trophoblastic cells,
like the cytotrophoblast and the syncytial trophoblast.
Well, in this particular disorder, you've got these abnormal villi, and the villi are very edematous,
and often surrounded by trophoblasts, sometimes excessive trophoblasts.
So it's these large edematous villi that actually pass through as grape-like masses,
and that's why the patient's passing these grape-like masses.
Now, more commonly in the West, where there might be prenatal care,
the patients wouldn't be diagnosed by the passing of grape-like masses,
but instead they would undergo routine ultrasound in the early first trimester.
And what would be found is that there is no baby, so the heart sounds would be absent.
And instead, you see all of these grape-like masses on ultrasound,
and those grape-like masses, because they're full of fluid,
they produce this white and black sort of discrepancy between where the masses are
and what's in between the masses, and that's called a snowstorm appearance.
So that's a classic finding an ultrasound when there is prenatal care.
So passing of grape-like masses if there is no prenatal care,
and a snowstorm appearance with a lack of fetal heart sounds if there is prenatal care.
Now, once you've made a decision that the patient has a molar pregnancy,
then the next thing you have to do is you have to classify that molar pregnancy.
And molar pregnancies can be classified as complete or partial.
Now, the classification of complete or partial is based on a few things.
So you look at the genetics, you look at the fetal tissue,
and you ask the question, is there any fetal tissue being made or not?
Sometimes there is, sometimes there isn't.
You look at how swollen the villi are.
Sometimes all of the villi are swollen.
Sometimes only some of the villi are swollen.
You look at the trophoblastic proliferation.
In these particular disorders, you've got the swollen villi,
and sometimes there will be excess trophoblasts all along the villus,
like from top to bottom,
and sometimes there will be excess trophoblastic proliferation
only on one end of the villus.
And so that's a question that you have to ask.
How extensive is the trophoblastic proliferation?
And all of these features are useful
for trying to subclassify a mole as partial or complete.
Now, you could sit here and try to memorize this chart,
and you probably could do it,
but I think there's a little bit of an easier way to remember this.
And for me, I always like to have a principle
and then try to be able to derive as many of the points
from that principle as possible.
So I'll tell you how I think about this,
and hopefully it'll be useful to you.
Now, the way I think about it is to understand why it's occurring.
So let's have a little discussion as to why this occurs.
As with most things in life, it's usually dad's fault, right?
So this actually is a disorder that is basically dad's fault.
Now, what happens is one possibility is that there is an egg,
an ovum, and the ovum is empty.
And two sperm come into that ovum.
So if two sperm come into that ovum,
that can result in a molar pregnancy.
Now, when two sperm come into an empty ovum,
all of the genetic material is dad, correct?
So that is a complete mole.
It is completely from dad.
All the genetic material is completely from dad.
So let's just ask a simple question.
If I only have two sperm in here,
then how many chromosomes would I have?
I would have 46 chromosomes.
So in a complete mole, you have only 46 chromosomes.
Now, another thing that we were going to look at
was whether fetal tissue was present or absent.
Well, I'll tell you that when you have an empty egg with two sperm,
i.e. a complete mole,
you don't get any fetal tissue.
So what could I,
the other way I could think about this
is it's completely a mole.
It's completely molar.
There's no other baby tissue there.
It's just all mole.
So that's a complete mole.
It's a complete mole.
There's no baby tissue.
Another thing we're going to look at
was the presence of villus edema,
the extent of villus edema, correct?
And you'll recall that you could either have
all of the moles,
sorry, all of the villi be edeminous
or some of the villi be edeminous.
And in a complete mole,
all of the villi are edeminous,
i.e. they're completely edeminous, okay?
And in a partial mole,
some of the villi are edeminous,
but we'll get there in a minute.
And then we were also going to ask the question
about trophoblastic proliferation.
Remember I said that in a molar pregnancy,
one of the key things is you have too many trophoblasts,
which are the cells that normally align the villus.
Well, it's possible that you could have
the excess trophoblast present
only along one side of the villus,
or the excess trophoblasts could be present
all along the villus,
all along the circumference of the villus.
And in a complete mole,
you get complete proliferation of the trophoblast,
and so you're going to have proliferation
of the trophoblasts all along the villus,
whereas in a partial mole,
it'll just be partially along the edematous villi.
And then another point we could raise is,
and I haven't put it in your chart here,
but just to help you remember,
one of the questions you can ask is about the beta-HCG.
Remember that in a complete mole,
the beta-HCG is much higher
than it would be in a partial mole.
And in a complete mole,
the reason why the beta-HCG is more higher
is because you have more trophoblastic proliferation,
and it's the syncytio trophoblasts
that actually make the beta-HCG.
So that becomes easy to remember as well.
And then finally,
the feared complication of a molar pregnancy
is chorio-carcinoma.
And we could ask the question,
which mole has a greater risk for chorio-carcinoma?
Well, the answer is that the complete mole
has the complete risk for chorio-carcinoma,
so it has the higher risk.
And the risk is about 2% to 3%.
So that's the notion of a complete mole.
Now let's read together from the chart in your book.
So what do I say here?
A complete mole is an empty egg fertilized by two sperm,
giving you 46 chromosomes.
Fetal tissue is absent.
It's completely molar.
There is villus edema,
and most villi, almost all villi, are hydropic.
Hydropic means that they're full of water.
They're edematous.
The trophoblastic proliferation is diffuse.
It completely involves the circumference of the villi.
And the risk for chorio-carcinoma is high.
It's 2% to 3%, relatively high.
Now let's look at partial mole.
And partial mole, the problem is that you've got a normal egg
with the chromosomal material of mom,
and two sperm come in and fertilize that normal egg.
So when two sperm come in and fertilize that normal egg,
we're now going to have 69 chromosomes, right?
46 from dad and 23 from mom.
Now fetal tissue, it's a partial mole,
so it'll have part fetus, part mole.
So fetal tissue will be present.
It's a partial mole,
so the villi will partially be edematous.
And there will be partial trophoblastic proliferation
around the circumference of those villi.
And there is a partial risk for chorio-carcinoma,
i.e. there is a relatively lower risk for chorio-carcinoma.
This is what the villi look like in a molar pregnancy.
You get these massively dilated villi,
and you get this trophoblastic proliferation
where there are too many trophoblasts.
Now the treatment of a molar pregnancy
is dilatation and curatage.
So basically what happens is you dilate the cervix,
and then you go in there,
and you curate out that molar pregnancy.
When that occurs,
the next thing you can do is measure the beta-HCG.
And the beta-HCG is helpful
because it helps to tell you that you removed the mole.
So once you do the DNC,
and you pull away the molar tissue,
you've now gotten rid of the mole,
and so therefore as you've gotten rid of the mole,
the beta-HCG should also go down.
So that's the way by which you ensure
that there's adequate removal of the molar tissue.
The other use for the beta-HCG
is to screen for the development of choriocarcinoma.
Now remember that the feared complication
of a molar pregnancy is choriocarcinoma.
If a woman has a molar pregnancy,
it's emotionally very distressing,
and it's inconvenient.
However, it's not potentially lethal.
What's potentially lethal
would be the development of a choriocarcinoma.
That's the feared complication
because that's a high-grade malignant tumor.
And so that's what we want to screen for,
and we can use the beta-HCG to screen for it.
We can ask the patient to come in
to get subsequent beta-HCG testing
over the next year, for example,
because it's usually within the first year
after the removal of the molar pregnancy
that a choriocarcinoma could classically develop.
So the beta-HCG is useful for screening
for the future development of choriocarcinoma
in these patients as well.
Now choriocarcinoma,
just very briefly touching on this,
remember that choriocarcinoma is what?
It's a tumor of trophoblasts.
So in a choriocarcinoma,
you have cytotrophoblasts and syncytiotrophoblasts.
The syncytiotrophoblasts produce beta-HCG,
and remember that there will be no villi.
You won't see villi.
You will only see the cytotrophoblasts
and the syncytiotrophoblasts,
and that's what defines choriocarcinoma.
Now, it's important to note
that if you put together the discussions
that we've had in this chapter,
remember that one of the subtypes of germ cell tumor
was a choriocarcinoma.
Now, that choriocarcinoma,
that has nothing to do with gestation.
It did not arise in a background of,
for example, a mole and a patient being pregnant
or thinking that they were pregnant.
So that is one way to get a choriocarcinoma,
which is as a germ cell tumor,
a spontaneous germ cell tumor.
Another way to get a choriocarcinoma
would be as a complication of gestation.
So, for example, about half of choriocarcinoma
arises as a complication of a molar pregnancy.
Sometimes choriocarcinoma can arise
as a complication of a spontaneous abortion.
as a complication even after a normal pregnancy.
Of course, choriocarcinoma is exceedingly rare,
very, very rare,
but this is still another way
by which that can occur.
So, you actually have two separate pathways
for choriocarcinoma.
Now, how do examiners go after this?
The way they test this is
the fact that the gestational pathway,
the pathway, for example, after a mole,
responds well to chemotherapy.
But remember I told you
that the germ cell pathway does not.
So this is the way by which examiners
will go after this
because it ensures to the examiners
that you actually understand
that choriocarcinoma is actually kind of two flavors.
So when choriocarcinoma arises as a complication,
just a normal spontaneous germ cell tumor,
then that will not respond well
to chemotherapy classically.
Whereas when choriocarcinoma arises
as a complication of gestation,
for example, after a molar pregnancy,
then that will respond very well to chemotherapy.
And it's amazing how these tumors
can respond to chemotherapy.
They literally can just melt and disappear.
So that's a very important distinction
both clinically, it's a practical principle,
it's a high-yield quote-unquote
high-yield topic to be aware of
or high-yield principle to be aware of.
So that concludes our discussion
of choriocarcinoma and gestational topics,
and that concludes our chapter as well.
Let's do it.